{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Article 359 of the Constitution authorizes the president of India to suspend the right to move any court for the enforcement of Fundamental Rights during :\n",
            "optionA": "  A National Emergency ",
            "optionB": "  A failure of constitutional machinery in States ",
            "optionC": "  A financial emergency ",
            "optionD": "  None of Above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhere a Proclamation of Emergency is in operation, the President may by order declare that the right to move any court for the enforcement of such of 1[the rights conferred by Part III (except articles 20 and 21)] as may be mentioned in the order and all proceedings pending in any court for the enforcement of the rights so mentioned shall remain suspended for the period during which the Proclamation is in force or for such shorter period as may be specified in the order. ",
            "keyString": "497244s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The correct chronological order of the formation of Haryana, Sikkim, Arunanchal Pradesh and Nagaland as full states of Indian Union is :",
            "optionA": "  Haryana-Sikkim-Arunachal Pardesh-Nagaland ",
            "optionB": "  Nagaland-Arunachal  Pradesh- Haryana-Sikkim ",
            "optionC": "  Nagaland-Haryana-Arunachal Pradesh-Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Nagaland-Haryana-Sikkim-Arunachal  Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagaland on 1st December 1963. Haryana on 1st November 1966. Sikkim on 16th May 1975. Arunachal Pradesh on 20th Feb 1987. ",
            "keyString": "497274s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The speaker of the Lok Sabha can ask a member of the house to stop speaking and let another member speak. This phenomenon is known as :\n",
            "optionA": "  Crossing the floor ",
            "optionB": "  Yielding the floor ",
            "optionC": "  Point of Order ",
            "optionD": "  Calling Attention Motion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:Yielding the floor. The speaker of the Lok sabha can ask a member of the house to stop speaking and let another member speak. Crossing the floor: Passing between the member addressing the House and the Chair which is considered breach of Parliamentary etiquette. Point of Order: A Member of Parliament may raise a point of order if he feels that the proceedings of' the House do not follow the normal rules. The presiding officer decides whether the point of order raised by the member should be allowed. Calling Attention Motion: With the prior permission of the Speaker, any member of the Parliament may call the attention of a Minister to a matter of urgent public importance. The Minister may make a brief statement about the matter or he may ask for time to make a statement later. ",
            "keyString": "497289s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By which Constitutional Amendment Act was the number of Lok sabha seats increased from 525 to 545 ?\n\n",
            "optionA": "   The Twentieth Amendment Act, 1966. ",
            "optionB": "  The Forty-second Amendment Act, 1976.  ",
            "optionC": "  The Forty-fourth Amendment Act, 1978. ",
            "optionD": "  Thirty-first Constitutional  Amendment  Act, 1973. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t31st Constitutional Amendment Act, 1973 - By this amendment the seats of Lok Sabha was increased from 525 to 545 but reduced the representatior of UT's in Lok Sabha from 25 to 20. ",
            "keyString": "497301s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Backward Class commission was appointed in 1953 under the chairmanship of :\n\n\u00a0\n",
            "optionA": "  Deepak Katole ",
            "optionB": "  S.K.Kharventhan ",
            "optionC": "  Kaka  Kalelkar ",
            "optionD": "  Shakeel-uz-Zaman Ansari ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:Kaka Kalelkar Commission:The Backward Class Commission was appointed in 1953 with Kaka Kalelkar as the Chairman. The Commission was asked to determine the criteria to be adopted to provide concessions to \u201csocially and educationally backward classes\u201d besides the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes; the Commission was also asked to prepare a list of such classes. ",
            "keyString": "497312s2m40h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "The first - ever Indian Railways Human Resources Round Table Conference has started in which city?",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Pune ",
            "optionD": "  Kochi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Union Minister of Railways Suresh Prabhakar Prabhu has inaugurated the first-ever Indian Railways Human Resources Round Table Conference in New Delhi on June 10, 2017. ",
            "keyString": "80284s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kacheguda railway station has declared the India\u2019s first Energy - Efficient \u2018A1 Category\u2019 Railway Station. It is situated in which city?",
            "optionA": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Kochi ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHyderabad's Kacheguda railway station becomes the first energy efficient station in India. The Kacheguda railway station in Hyderabad, Telangana, has been declared as the first energy-efficient railway station in the country, which now also falls under the A1 category. ",
            "keyString": "80314s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India\u2019s first - ever railways disaster management centre will come up in which city?",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionC": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionD": "  Pune ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's first-ever railways disaster management centre is expected to come up near Bengaluru, Karnataka by 2018 and will be used to replicate train accidents to improve rescue operation efforts. ",
            "keyString": "80327s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ministry of Railways has signed MoU with which Union Ministry to augment services in Railway hospitals?",
            "optionA": "  Ministry of Women and Child Development ",
            "optionB": "  Ministry of Drinking Water and Sanitation ",
            "optionC": "  Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment ",
            "optionD": "  Ministry of AYUSH ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Memorandum of Understanding was signed between Ministry of Railways and Ministry of AYUSH in New Delhi today to augment the AYUSH system services in its zonal hospitals at New Delhi, Mumbai, Kolkata, Chennai and Guwahati. ",
            "keyString": "80340s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which road suburban railway station in Mumbai has been rechristened as Prabhadevi station?",
            "optionA": "  Boisar ",
            "optionB": "  Andheri ",
            "optionC": "  Churchgate ",
            "optionD": "  Elphinstone ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe name of Elphinstone Road railway station officially changed to Prabhadevi from July 19, 2018. ",
            "keyString": "80351s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Railways is constructing the country\u2019s longest railway tunnel and tallest bridge in which of the following states?",
            "optionA": "  Manipur and Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "optionB": "  Jammu & Kashmir & Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Assam and Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra and Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe longest of these tunnels will be 11.55 km long, making it India's longest tunnel under construction. Also, India will soon boast the world's tallest railway bridge, construction of which is on in full swing, over the river Chenab in the hostile terrain of Jammu and Kashmir. ",
            "keyString": "113380s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "General Manager is responsible for",
            "optionA": "  Railway Board ",
            "optionB": "  Railway Ministry ",
            "optionC": "  Both railway Board and Railway Ministry ",
            "optionD": "  Finance Ministry ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGeneral Manager is responsible for Railway Board. ",
            "keyString": "113409s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Over which of the following rivers is the world's highest railway bridge in Kashmir being constructed?",
            "optionA": "  Chenab ",
            "optionB": "  Jhelum ",
            "optionC": "  Sutlej ",
            "optionD": "  Indus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chenab Bridge is an Indian railway steel and concrete arch bridge under construction between Bakkal and Kauri in the Reasi district of Jammu and Kashmir in India. When completed, the bridge will span the Chenab River at a height of 359 m (1,178 ft) above the river, making it the world's highest rail bridge. ",
            "keyString": "113422s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements: 1. Anti - collision device (ACD) Network is patented by Konkan Railway Corporation Ltd. 2. Anti - collision device (ACD) uses Global Positioning System for its work Which among the above statements is / are correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 is true ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 is true ",
            "optionC": "  Both are true ",
            "optionD": "  Neither is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnti - collision device (ACD) Network is patented by Konkan Railway Corporation Ltd. and Anti - collision device (ACD) uses Global Positioning System for its work. ",
            "keyString": "113433s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In recent times, the \u201cdynamic brake system\u201d is becoming popular in modern railways. The dynamic brake system coverts Kinetic energy to________:",
            "optionA": "  Potential energy ",
            "optionB": "  Electricity ",
            "optionC": "  Sound energy ",
            "optionD": "  Magnetic energy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe dynamic brake system coverts Kinetic energy to electricity. ",
            "keyString": "113447s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Read the Following Railway Headquarters and Identify which is False?",
            "optionA": "  South - Central Railway - Secunderabad ",
            "optionB": "  Central railway - Bhopal ",
            "optionC": "  South Railway - Chennai ",
            "optionD": "  North Railway - New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentral railway - Bhopal is wrong because central railway has its headquarters in Mumbai. ",
            "keyString": "146761s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following cities are located 3 zonal headquarters of Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Guwahati ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKolkata gets the trophy for having 3 Zonal Headquarters of Indian Railways. ",
            "keyString": "146790s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following zonal headquarters - city combination is incorrect?",
            "optionA": "  South East Central - Bilaspur ",
            "optionB": "  North Western - Jodhpur ",
            "optionC": "  East Central - Hajipur ",
            "optionD": "  West Central - Jabalpur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth Western - Jodhpur is incorrect. ",
            "keyString": "146804s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of South Railways is situated at",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Mumbai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSouthern Railway has its headquarters in Chennai. ",
            "keyString": "146817s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of South - Central Railways is situated at",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai (CST) ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Secunderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Mumbai (Central) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of South - Central Railways is situated at Secunderabad. ",
            "keyString": "146829s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cancellation facility through ________ helpline number will be provided using 'One Time Password' sent on registered phone number.",
            "optionA": "  144 ",
            "optionB": "  123 ",
            "optionC": "  139 ",
            "optionD": "  119 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCancellation facility through 139 helpline number will be provided using 'One Time Password' sent on registered phone number. ",
            "keyString": "178957s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements with regard to \u2018Ad Hoc\u2019 Committees of the parliament:1)They are temporary in nature and appointed for a specific purpose2)Railway Convention Committee is an ad hoc committeeWhich among the above statements is / are correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 is correct ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 is correct ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 are correct ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 is correct ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey are temporary in nature and appointed for a specific purpose and Railway Convention Committee is an ad hoc committee. ",
            "keyString": "178985s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indian Railways has launched which virtual server to optimise server usage and faster connectivity?",
            "optionA": "  RailSagar ",
            "optionB": "  RailCloud ",
            "optionC": "  RailSilver ",
            "optionD": "  RailBharat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t In a significant IT initiative, the Railways launched RailCloud - a virtual server with an inbuilt security system to optimise server usage and faster connectivity. ",
            "keyString": "179001s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The passenger bogies of the Indian Railways are manufactured at which of the following places?",
            "optionA": "  Kapurthala ",
            "optionB": "  Chittranjan ",
            "optionC": "  Perambur ",
            "optionD": "  Bangalore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe passenger bogies of the Indian Railways are manufactured at Perambur. ",
            "keyString": "179013s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gorakhpur which has the longest railway platform in the world is located in which of the following states?",
            "optionA": "  Odisha ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Chhattisgarh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Gorakhpur Railway Station is located in the city of Gorakhpur in the Indian state of Uttar Pradesh. It has the world's longest railway platform. It serves as the headquarters of the North Eastern Railway. ",
            "keyString": "179024s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements with respect to the Railway Convention Committee:1)The committee consists of members only from Lok Sabha2)Railway Minister is the ex - officio chairman of Railway Convention CommitteeWhich of the above statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeither 1 nor 2 ",
            "keyString": "213106s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With respect to \u2018Operating ratio\u2019 in Railways, which of the following statement is/are correct?1)The higher is the \u2018Operating Ratio\u2019; the better is the economic condition of railways.2) \u2018Operating ratio\u2019 of Indian Railways is high on account of social service obligation imposed in Budget.Select the correct option from the codes given below",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Operating ratio\u2019 of Indian Railways is high on account of social service obligation imposed in Budget. ",
            "keyString": "213136s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "New Humsafar Express, 3 - tier AC train was flagged off between which two locations on 2 June 2018?",
            "optionA": "  Ajmer and Rameshwaram ",
            "optionB": "  Gorakhpur and Anand Vihar ",
            "optionC": "  Agartala and Bengaluru ",
            "optionD": "  Jodhpur and Bandra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew Humsafar Express Flagged Off between Jodhpur and Bandra. Union Railway Minister, Piyush Goyal flagged off a new Humsafar Jodhpur Bandra Express. The train started its journey towards Bandra from Bhagat Ki Kothi Railway station in Rajasthan's Jodhpur on 2nd June 2018. ",
            "keyString": "213152s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the India's first double Decker train?",
            "optionA": "  Ahmedabad - Mumbai Central Double Decker Express ",
            "optionB": "  Samjhauta Express ",
            "optionC": "  Guwahati Thiruvananthapuram Express ",
            "optionD": "  Howrah \u2013 Dhanbad Double Decker Express ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "213163s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "TCAS full form is:",
            "optionA": "  Train Collision Advance System ",
            "optionB": "  Train Complement Accident Software ",
            "optionC": "  Train Collision Avoidance Software ",
            "optionD": "  Traffic Collision Avoidance System ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTraffic Collision Avoidance System. ",
            "keyString": "213174s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the length of North - Eastern Frontier Railway (NEFR)?",
            "optionA": "  4300 Km ",
            "optionB": "  3700 Km ",
            "optionC": "  4290 km ",
            "optionD": "  5298 km ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe length of North - Eastern Frontier Railway (NEFR) is 3700 Km. ",
            "keyString": "245973s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who invented the railway engine?",
            "optionA": "  Charles Babbage ",
            "optionB": "  Isaac Newton ",
            "optionC": "  James Watt ",
            "optionD": "  George Stephenson ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1825 George Stephenson built the Locomotion for the Stockton and Darlington Railway. This was the first public steam railway in the world and then in 1829, he built The Rocket which was entered in and won the Rainhill Trials. ",
            "keyString": "246002s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many members did the railway board had?",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  5 ",
            "optionC": "  4 ",
            "optionD": "  8 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailway board had 4 members. ",
            "keyString": "246015s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main objective of British developing Indian Railway system was to facilitate the traffic between?",
            "optionA": "  Source of raw material and export centers ",
            "optionB": "  Source of raw material and ports ",
            "optionC": "  Source of raw material and production centers ",
            "optionD": "  Source of raw material and markets ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main objective of British developing Indian Railway system was to facilitate the traffic between source of raw material and production centers. ",
            "keyString": "246027s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ percent sub - quota for women under all reserved categories",
            "optionA": "  30 ",
            "optionB": "  35 ",
            "optionC": "  33 ",
            "optionD": "  40 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailways has introduced 33% of sub-quota for women in the allotment of food stalls at rail premises as a special provision in the new catering policy. ",
            "keyString": "246038s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the fastest train in India?",
            "optionA": "  Rajdhani Express ",
            "optionB": "  Shatabdi Express ",
            "optionC": "  Duronto Express ",
            "optionD": "  Tejas Express ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe fastest train in India is Tejas Express. ",
            "keyString": "279502s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state has the longest route (in kilometers) of railway line in India?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India, the largest route kilometers are in Uttar Pradesh with 8726 kilometers. ",
            "keyString": "279530s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As per the recent survey conducted by the Quality Council of India, which railway stations have been named as the cleanest and dirtiest railway stations in India?",
            "optionA": "  Darbhanga and Allahabad ",
            "optionB": "  Allahabad and Indore ",
            "optionC": "  Indore and Visakhapatnam ",
            "optionD": "  Visakhapatnam and Darbhanga ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "279543s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Zone is the largest railway zone in India?",
            "optionA": "  Central Railway ",
            "optionB": "  Northern Railway ",
            "optionC": "  Eastern Railway ",
            "optionD": "  Western Railway ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorthern Railway zone is the Answer. Its headquarter is New Delhi Railway Station. Northern Railways is one of nine old zones of Indian Railways and also the biggest in terms of network having 6807 kilometre route. ",
            "keyString": "279555s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which country was flange wheel invented?",
            "optionA": "  Germany ",
            "optionB": "  Japan ",
            "optionC": "  Europe ",
            "optionD": "  Russia ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFlange wheel was invented in Germany. ",
            "keyString": "279566s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Metro Railway is functioning in which of the following Indian States?",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMetro Railway is functioning in West Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "312084s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first locomotive which was manufactured in Chittaranjan on",
            "optionA": "  Nov - 1950 ",
            "optionB": "  Oct - 1950 ",
            "optionC": "  Sep - 1949 ",
            "optionD": "  Oct - 1954 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 1 November, 1950, Indian President Dr. Rajendra Prasad formally dedicated the first steam rail-engine produced by the company (a WG class locomotive bearing the registration number 8401) to the freedom fighter Deshbandhu Chittranjan Das. ",
            "keyString": "312113s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Introduced ________ in Konkan Railway to help old and disabled passengers.",
            "optionA": "  Sahayak Express ",
            "optionB": "  Viklang Seva Express ",
            "optionC": "  Divyang Express ",
            "optionD": "  Sarathi Seva ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSarathi Seva ",
            "keyString": "312126s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the new Harbour rail line inaugurated?",
            "optionA": "  1925 ",
            "optionB": "  1928 ",
            "optionC": "  1931 ",
            "optionD": "  1933 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Harbour line is a branch line of the Mumbai Suburban Railway operated by Central Railway. It was named so because it catered to the eastern neighbourhoods along the city's natural harbour. Its termini are Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Terminus (CSMT), Andheri/Goregaon and Panvel on the CSMT-Goregaon, CSMT-Panvel and Panvel-Andheri routes. The first section of the line, between Kurla and Reay Road, opened on 12 December 1910. In 1925, the line was connected to the then Victoria Terminus via an elevated rail corridor between Dockyard Road and Sandhurst Road. ",
            "keyString": "312137s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year palace on wheels train inaugurated?",
            "optionA": "  1988 ",
            "optionB": "  1978 ",
            "optionC": "  1982 ",
            "optionD": "  1965 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWith a noble motive to promote tourism in Rajasthan, the Rajasthan Tourism Development Corporation along with Indian Railway launched the first Indian luxury train Palace on Wheels on 26th January' 1982. ",
            "keyString": "312148s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where did Chapman form the committee?",
            "optionA": "  Glassgo ",
            "optionB": "  London ",
            "optionC": "  Edimbara ",
            "optionD": "  Lords ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "345527s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Maitree Express connects India with which of the following countries?",
            "optionA": "  Myanmar ",
            "optionB": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionC": "  Bangladesh ",
            "optionD": "  Nepal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Maitree Express or Dhaka-Kolkata Express is an International passenger train serving the railway connecting the Bangladeshi capital of Dhaka and India's West Bengal (Paschim Banga) states capital Kolkata. This is the only railway link between the cities of the two nations. ",
            "keyString": "345555s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fairy Queen, the world's oldest steam locomotive in regular operation, plies between New Delhi and ________",
            "optionA": "  Shimla ",
            "optionB": "  Alwar ",
            "optionC": "  Kalka ",
            "optionD": "  Gwalior ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt occasionally runs between New Delhi and Alwar. In 1998 it was listed in the Guinness Book of Records as the world's oldest steam locomotive in regular service. The Fairy Queen runs on the same route as the Palace on Wheels, the tourist train launched in 1982, and in 1999 was awarded a National Tourism Award. ",
            "keyString": "345568s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who will be called Sahayak?",
            "optionA": "  New Superfast Train ",
            "optionB": "  Upcoming Event made for Disabled Persons ",
            "optionC": "  Coolies ",
            "optionD": "  Railway Magazine (including Railway's upcoming ventures) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoolies will be called sahayaks. ",
            "keyString": "345580s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mission PACE deals with",
            "optionA": "  Protection of nature ",
            "optionB": "  Help Customers ",
            "optionC": "  Fast Ticketing System ",
            "optionD": "  Quality of Goods and Services ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMission PACE (Procurement and Consumption Efficiency): This mission aims to improve our procurement and consumption practices to improve the quality of goods and services.",
            "keyString": "345590s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state government has recently signed MoU with Indian Railways to expand green cover?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn a bid to expand the green cover, the Maharashtra government recently signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with the Indian Railways, under which trees will be planted on the land adjacent to the railway tracks in the state. ",
            "keyString": "378269s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which research arm of Indian Railways has launched \u201cNew Online Vendor Registration System\u201d?",
            "optionA": "  Indian Railway Institute of Signal Engineering and Telecommunication ",
            "optionB": "  Research Designs and Standards Organisation ",
            "optionC": "  National Academy of Indian Railways ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Railway Service of Electrical Engineers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearch Designs and Standards Organisation has launched \u201cNew Online Vendor Registration System\". ",
            "keyString": "378297s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following was the first Railway Minister of independent India?",
            "optionA": "  John Mathai ",
            "optionB": "  Lal Bahadur Shastri ",
            "optionC": "  Jawaharlal Nehru ",
            "optionD": "  Shanmugham Shetty ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJohn Mathai was the first Railway Minister of independent India. ",
            "keyString": "378311s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest national enterprise of India is",
            "optionA": "  Indian Railway ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Shipyard ",
            "optionC": "  Airways ",
            "optionD": "  Waterways ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railway is the largest national enterprise of India. ",
            "keyString": "378322s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about Operating Ratio in Indian Railways:1)The higher the operating ratio of Indian Railways the better is the condition of Indian Railways. 2)Operating ratio of Indian Railways is high on account of social service obligation imposed in Budget.Which of the above statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOperating ratio of Indian Railways is high on account of social service obligation imposed in Budget. ",
            "keyString": "378335s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Speaker of Lok Sabha also works as the ex - officio Chairperson of which of the following committees?1)Railway Convention Committee2)Business Advisory Committee3)Public Account CommitteeSelect the correct option from the codes given below:",
            "optionA": "  1 & 2 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  1 & 3 Only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Speaker of Lok Sabha also works as the ex - officio Chairperson of Business Advisory Committee. ",
            "keyString": "413120s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following faunal species found in India are invasive species?1)Railway Creeper2)Lantana3)Black wattleSelect the correct option from the codes given below:",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 1 & 2 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 2 & 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "413155s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is / are Union Subjects as per seventh schedule of the Constitution of India?1)Armed Forces2)Paramilitary Forces3)Railway Police4)Cantonment AreasSelect the correct option from the codes given below:",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 & 2 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 1, 2 & 3 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 1, 2 & 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2, 3 & 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOnly 1, 2 & 4 ",
            "keyString": "413173s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following becomes the part of Consolidated Fund of India?1)Capitation Taxes2)Taxes on railway fares and freights3)Taxes on sale and purchase of newspapers and advertisements thereinSelect the correct option from the codes given below:",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 & 2 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 & 3 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 3 ",
            "optionD": "  None of them ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNone of them ",
            "keyString": "413191s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is / are eligible to receive Ways and Means Advances from RBI to handle their temporary mismatch in the cash flow?1)State Governments2)Central Government3)Public Sector Companies4)Indian RailwaysSelect the correct option from the codes given below:",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 1 & 2 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 1 & 3 ",
            "optionD": "  Only 1, 3 & 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tState governments ",
            "keyString": "413207s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of North - Eastern railway is situated at",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai (CST) ",
            "optionB": "  Guwahati ",
            "optionC": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "optionD": "  New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe North Eastern Railway is one of the 18 railway zones in India. It is headquartered at Gorakhpur and comprises Lucknow, Varanasi and Izzatnagar or Bareilly division. ",
            "keyString": "446723s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of Northern Railway is at",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Guwahati ",
            "optionC": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "optionD": "  Mumbai (CST) ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Northern Railway (abbreviated NR and \u0909\u0930\u0947) is one of the 18 Railway zones of India and the northernmost zone of the Indian Railways. Its headquarter is New Delhi Baroda House near India Gate. ",
            "keyString": "446752s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following railway zones with their headquarters:West Central Railway\u2192 Jabalpur East Coast Railway \u2192 Bhubaneswar Western Railway\u2192 MumbaiWhich of the above is / are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 & 2 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 & 3 Only ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll are correct. ",
            "keyString": "446765s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of the South Central Railway zone is located in?",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Secunderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe headquarters of the South Central Railway zone is located in Secunderabad. ",
            "keyString": "446780s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following:Road and Railways Schools Sanitary Facilities HospitalsWhich among the above are considered to be the Economic Overheads?",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  1 & 2 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 , 3 & 4 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRoad and Railways are considered to be the Economic Overheads. ",
            "keyString": "446792s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following sectors are included as part of multi - modal logistics hubs in India?1)Aviation2)National Highways3) Ports4)Inland waterways5)RailwaysSelect the correct option from codes given below:",
            "optionA": "  Only 2, 3 & 4 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2, 3, 4, 5 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2, 3, 4 & 5 ",
            "optionD": "  Only 2, 3 & 5 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "500252s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has been appointed as the new Chairman of Railway Board?",
            "optionA": "  V K Yadav ",
            "optionB": "  A K Mittal ",
            "optionC": "  P S Thakur ",
            "optionD": "  Neelmani Reddy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVinod Kumar Yadav, the South Central Railway (SCR) general manager, has been appointed as Chairman of the Railway Board under the Ministry of Railways and ex-officio Principal Secretary to the Government of India. He succeeded Ashwani Lohani. ",
            "keyString": "500284s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rajasthan is under which of the following railway zones?",
            "optionA": "  Northern region ",
            "optionB": "  Western region ",
            "optionC": "  North - Western region ",
            "optionD": "  Central Region ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajasthan is included under North-western Railway zone which is one among the 17 railway zones of India. Its headquarter is at Jaipur. It comprises of four divisions: Jodhpur, Bikaner, Jaipur and Ajmer divisions. ",
            "keyString": "500296s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Railways has recently signed pact with which company for use of Natural Gas in railway workshops?",
            "optionA": "  ONGC ",
            "optionB": "  GAIL India ",
            "optionC": "  NTPC ",
            "optionD": "  IOCL ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn New Delhi, Indian Railways has recently signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MoU) with GAIL India Ltd for use of environment-friendly fuel 'Natural Gas' in Railway workshops and production units. ",
            "keyString": "500308s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Besides Maharashtra, Karnataka and Goa, which of the following is the fourth State for Konakan Railway Project?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKerala is the fourth state. ",
            "keyString": "500319s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarters of North - East Frontier Railway (NFR) is",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Maligaon (Guwahati) ",
            "optionC": "  Chennai ",
            "optionD": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Northeast Frontier Railway (abbreviated NFR), is one of the 18 railway zones in India. Headquartered in Maligaon, Guwahati in the state of Assam, it is responsible for rail operations in the entire Northeast and parts of West Bengal and Bihar. ",
            "keyString": "532068s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ministry of Railways has recently launched which app for freight managers?",
            "optionA": "  SFOORTI app ",
            "optionB": "  SKOORTI app ",
            "optionC": "  SNOORTI app ",
            "optionD": "  SMOORTI app ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn a major digital initiative to help plan the traffic flows and optimize freight operations, Ministry of Railways has launched Smart Freight Operation Optimisation and Real Time Information (SFOORTI) App for freight managers. ",
            "keyString": "532098s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Launched World's first Bio Toilet Train. Named as:",
            "optionA": "  Deen Dayalu Express ",
            "optionB": "  Himsagar janshatabdi Express ",
            "optionC": "  Dirubharg Rajdhani Express ",
            "optionD": "  Shatabdi Express ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirubharg Rajdhani Express is world's first Bio Toilet Train. ",
            "keyString": "532111s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Rangpo - Sivok Railway line, connects which among the following two states of India?",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh \u2194 Tripura ",
            "optionB": "  Sikkim \u2194 West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  West Bengal \u2194 Tripura ",
            "optionD": "  Arunachal Pradesh \u2194 Assam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rangpo - Sivok Railway line, connects Sikkim to West Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "532123s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Matheran Hill Railway is located in which state of India?",
            "optionA": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionC": "  Odisha ",
            "optionD": "  Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMatheran is a hill station, near Mumbai, in the west Indian state of Maharashtra. ",
            "keyString": "532134s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following initiative with Ministries associated to them:1)Project Swarna \u2013 Ministry of Railways2)Project CHAMAN \u2013 Ministry of Agriculture 3)Project DARPAN \u2013 Ministry of CommunicationsWhich of the above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 & 2 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 & 3 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 1 & 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll three are correct. ",
            "keyString": "566124s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about the Bio Toilet Project in Indian Railways:1)The bio - toilets are joint initiative of Indian Railways and DRDO2)The human excreta in the bio - toilets is treated through anaerobic digestion process3)The bio toilet reduces the solid human waste to biogas and pure waterWhich of the above statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 & 3 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  2 & 3 Only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll three are correct. ",
            "keyString": "566160s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about the proposed Rail Development Authority:1)It will act within the parameters of the Railway Act, 19892)The authority will consist of four members3)It will regulate the sector opened to the private sector for investmentWhich of the above statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 & 2 Only ",
            "optionB": "  3 Only ",
            "optionC": "  2 & 3 Only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll three are correct. ",
            "keyString": "566179s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did the first ignition engine develop?",
            "optionA": "  1890 ",
            "optionB": "  1892 ",
            "optionC": "  1900 ",
            "optionD": "  1904 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1879, Karl Benz patented a reliable two-stroke gas engine. In 1892, Rudolf Diesel developed the first compressed charge, compression ignition engine. In 1926, Robert Goddard launched the first liquid-fueled rocket. ",
            "keyString": "566197s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the first train steamed off in India?",
            "optionA": "  1848 ",
            "optionB": "  1853 ",
            "optionC": "  1875 ",
            "optionD": "  1880 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn April 16,1853, the first passengers train steamed between Bori Bunder in Bombay and Thane. ",
            "keyString": "566209s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After Uttar Pradesh, which among the following states has the maximum share in the total Route Kilometers of Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionB": "  Maharastra ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAfter Uttar Pradesh, Rajasthan has the maximum share in the total Route Kilometers of Indian Railways. ",
            "keyString": "597922s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which country did India sign the Joint Declaration of Intent (JDI) to strengthen the cooperation on strategic projects in the field of Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Sweden ",
            "optionB": "  Russia ",
            "optionC": "  Germany ",
            "optionD": "  Italy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Union Cabinet chaired by the Prime Minister Narendra Modi was apprised of the Joint Declaration of Intent (JDI) between India and Germany regarding cooperation on strategic projects in the field of Railways. ",
            "keyString": "597952s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the easternmost division of the Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Tinsukia ",
            "optionB": "  Lumding ",
            "optionC": "  Rangiya ",
            "optionD": "  Katihar ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLekhapani is a railway station on the Lumding-Dibrugarh section. It is located in Tinsukia district in the Indian state of Assam. ",
            "keyString": "597968s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has been appointed as the new Union Minister of Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Piyush Goyal ",
            "optionB": "  Nirmala Sitharaman ",
            "optionC": "  Dharmendra Pradhan ",
            "optionD": "  Mukhtar Abbas Naqvi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPiyush Goyal is the current Union Minister for Railways. ",
            "keyString": "597980s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has been declared the cleanest railway station in the A1 category, as per 2018 cleanliness survey for Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Jaipur ",
            "optionB": "  Tirupati ",
            "optionC": "  Jodhpur ",
            "optionD": "  Warangal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRajasthan's Jodhpur and Marwar railway stations are the cleanest on the Indian Railways network, says a 2018 survey by the national transporter. ",
            "keyString": "597992s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following steps in Budget Procedure in India:1)The demands for grants of various ministries and departments including railways are considered by the concerned standing committees2)Broad contours of the budget and the principles and policies underlying it are discussed. 3)A cut motion is moved in the Lok Sabha 4)Budget is presented in the House.Which among the following is the correct sequence of the above steps?",
            "optionA": "  1 2 3 4 ",
            "optionB": "  1 2 4 3 ",
            "optionC": "  4 2 1 3 ",
            "optionD": "  3 1 4 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBudget is presented in the House, Broad contours of the budget and the principles and policies underlying it are discussed, The demands for grants of various ministries and departments including railways are considered by the concerned standing committees and A cut motion is moved in the Lok Sabha. ",
            "keyString": "631241s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the current director general of Railway Protection Force (RPF)?",
            "optionA": "  Brij Mohanty ",
            "optionB": "  S H Prakash ",
            "optionC": "  Dharmendra Kumar ",
            "optionD": "  Arun Kumar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn September 2018, Senior IPS officer Arun Kumar was appointed as Director General of Railway Protection Force (RPF). Kumar, a 1985 batch officer of the Uttar Pradesh cadre, is serving as Special Director General of Border Security Force. ",
            "keyString": "631275s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which app has been launched by the Ministry of Railways to expedite & streamline passenger grievance redressal?",
            "optionA": "  Rail Sathi ",
            "optionB": "  Rail Dost ",
            "optionC": "  Rail Madad ",
            "optionD": "  Rail Neer ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn line with digital initiatives of Hon'ble PM, Indian Railways has for the first time completely digitized the Complaint management system. Shri Piyush Goyal, Minister of Railways & Coal today launched a new App \u201cRail Madad\u201d \u2013 An App to expedite & streamline passenger grievance redressal. ",
            "keyString": "631290s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many stations to be redeveloped through PPP?",
            "optionA": "  100 ",
            "optionB": "  200 ",
            "optionC": "  350 ",
            "optionD": "  600 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Railways is under huge pressure to put the process of redeveloping the Railway Stations on a fast track. Earlier, there was a proposal to develop 400 stations.However, after the re-categorisation of stations which was done earlier this year the number of stations that need to be redeveloped has escalated to 600. ",
            "keyString": "631302s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which city is the Wheel and Axle Plant of the Indian Railways located?",
            "optionA": "  Kapurthala ",
            "optionB": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionC": "  Bangalore ",
            "optionD": "  Rae Barelly ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRail Wheel Factory, Yelehanka (RWF) (also known as Wheel and Axle Plant) is a manufacturing unit of Indian Railways, producing wheels, axles and wheel sets of railroad wagons, coaches and locomotives for the use of Indian Railways and overseas customers is situated at Yelahanka, Bangalore in the Indian state of Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "631313s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following ran the first train from Bori Bunder to Thane in 1853?",
            "optionA": "  Bombay Baroda Railway ",
            "optionB": "  The Scindia Railway ",
            "optionC": "  Central India Railway ",
            "optionD": "  Great Indian Peninsula Railway ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 16 April 1853, the Great Indian Peninsula Railway operated the first passenger train in India from Bori Bunder to Thane with 14 carriages and 400 passengers. The train which had three named locomotives, viz., Sindh, Sultan and Sahib, took off and embarked on an hour-and-fifteen-minute journey to Thane. ",
            "keyString": "664255s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Railway Staff College located?",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Vadodara ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe National Academy of Indian Railways, Vadodara formerly Railway Staff College is a Centralised Training Institute for Group A and B Officers of Indian Railways, headed by a Director General and manned by an faculty of experienced Railway Managers and Experts. ",
            "keyString": "664284s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The railway station situated in the extreme south is",
            "optionA": "  Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Cochin ",
            "optionC": "  Kanyakumari ",
            "optionD": "  Trivandrum ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe railway station situated in the extreme south is Kanyakumari. ",
            "keyString": "664298s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the construction work for the first Railway line Started?",
            "optionA": "  1821 ",
            "optionB": "  1828 ",
            "optionC": "  1823 ",
            "optionD": "  1830 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "664310s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many institutions do give suggestions for railways technology?",
            "optionA": "  One ",
            "optionB": "  Two ",
            "optionC": "  Three ",
            "optionD": "  Four ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo institutions do give suggestions for railways technology. ",
            "keyString": "664322s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Railway\u2019s Jamalpur Workshop is located at?",
            "optionA": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionB": "  Orissa ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railway\u2019s Jamalpur Workshop is located at Bihar. ",
            "keyString": "696442s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India's first rail auto hub will be located in:",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's first rail-auto transportation and logistics hub will come up in Walajabad, near Chennai, Tamil Nadu.",
            "keyString": "696469s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mountain Railways of India refer to the railway lines built in the mountains of India in the nineteenth and early twentieth century, during the British Raj, even being run today by the Indian Railways. How many railway lines refer to the Mountain Railways of India ?",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  5 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMountain Railways of India:(i)Darjeeling Himalayan Railways (DHR) - inscribed by UNESCO in 1999 :The Darjeeling Himalayan Railway consists of 88.48 kilometres of 2 feet (0.610 metre) gauge track that connects New Jalpaiguri with Darjeeling, passing through Ghoom at an altitude of 2,258 metres. The innovative design includes six zigzag reverses and three loops with a ruling gradient of 1:31. (ii) Nilgiri Mountain Railways (NMR) inscribed in 2005:This railway, scaling an elevation of 326 metre to 2,203 metre, represented the latest technology of the time and uses unique rack and pinion traction arrangement to negotiate steep gradient. (iii) Kalka Shimla Railway (KSR) inscribed in 2008: The world\u2019s highest multi-arch gallery bridge and the world\u2019s longest tunnel (at the time of construction) of KSR were the testimony of the brilliance engineering skills applied to make a dream a reality.",
            "keyString": "696482s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the position of the Indian Railway under one management are also credited with having a multi gauge and multi traction system?",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSecond position ",
            "keyString": "696494s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the name of the first train of Indian Railways handed over to private players for operation?",
            "optionA": "  Tejas Express ",
            "optionB": "  Shatabdi Express ",
            "optionC": "  Karnataka Express ",
            "optionD": "  Duronto Express ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Delhi-Lucknow Tejas Express is set to be the first train to be operated by private players, sources said Monday, indicating that the Railways is going ahead with its 100-day agenda of handing over operations of two of its trains to the private sector, despite protests from its unions. ",
            "keyString": "696505s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A platform surrounded by rail lines from all the four sides, is called",
            "optionA": "  Dock platform ",
            "optionB": "  Passenger platform ",
            "optionC": "  Island platform ",
            "optionD": "  Goods platform ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA platform surrounded by rail lines from all the four sides, is called Island platform. ",
            "keyString": "729581s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A station where the rail lines end, is called",
            "optionA": "  Junction station ",
            "optionB": "  Way - side station ",
            "optionC": "  Block station ",
            "optionD": "  Terminal station ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA \"terminus\" or \"terminal\" is a station at the end of a railway line. ",
            "keyString": "729609s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The zone with the minimum length is",
            "optionA": "  North - Eastern Railway ",
            "optionB": "  North - Eastern Frontier Railway ",
            "optionC": "  South - East Railway ",
            "optionD": "  South - Central Railway ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe zone with the minimum length is North - Eastern Frontier Railway. ",
            "keyString": "729623s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following cities is the National Rail Museum located ?",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Rail Museum is located in New Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "729635s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kandaghat, a heritage railway station made entirely of wood and built by the British in 1903 was destroyed in the fire. In which state this Railway Station was located ?",
            "optionA": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Maharastra ",
            "optionC": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu & Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Shimla-Kalka rail line has been declared as heritage site by UNESCO. The railway station building was made entirely of wood by Britishers in 1903. In a major fire incident, the 108 year old heritage Kandaghat railway station in Solan district of Himachal Pradesh was gutted on Tuesday wee hours. ",
            "keyString": "729647s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year Research, Design and Standard organization was established?",
            "optionA": "  1954 ",
            "optionB": "  1957 ",
            "optionC": "  1959 ",
            "optionD": "  1967 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1957, the Central Standards Office (CSO) and the Railway Testing and Research Centre (RTRC) were integrated into a single unit named Research Designs and Standards Organisation (RDSO) under the Ministry of Railways with its headquarters at Manak Nagar, Lucknow. ",
            "keyString": "760864s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the North - Eastern frontier Railway (NEFR) established?",
            "optionA": "  15th Jan, 1958 ",
            "optionB": "  15th Jan, 1955 ",
            "optionC": "  2nd Jan, 1956 ",
            "optionD": "  14th April, 1952 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe North - Eastern frontier Railway (NEFR) wasestablished in 15th January, 1958. ",
            "keyString": "760891s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the Central Railway established?",
            "optionA": "  5th Nov 1951 ",
            "optionB": "  14th Nov 1951 ",
            "optionC": "  14th April 1951 ",
            "optionD": "  16th August, 1951 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Central Railway was established 5th November, 1951. ",
            "keyString": "760904s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which of the following places Diesel Component Works is established?",
            "optionA": "  Jamshedpur ",
            "optionB": "  Patiala ",
            "optionC": "  Perambur ",
            "optionD": "  Varanasi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDiesel Component Works is established at Patiala. ",
            "keyString": "760916s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Railways has launched an integrated mobile app \u201cRail Saarthi\u201d for railway passengers. What does \u201cSaarthi\u201d stands for?",
            "optionA": "  Synergised Advanced Application Rail Travel Help and Information ",
            "optionB": "  Synchronic Advanced Application Rail Travel Help and Information ",
            "optionC": "  Synchronous Advanced Application Rail Travel Help and Information ",
            "optionD": "  Synergic Advanced Application Rail Travel Help and Information ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSynergised Advanced Application Rail Travel Help and Information",
            "keyString": "760927s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The manufacturing of steam engine in Chittranjan Locomotive Works was stopped in",
            "optionA": "  1974 ",
            "optionB": "  1961 ",
            "optionC": "  1972 ",
            "optionD": "  1973 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe production of steam and diesel locomotives were discontinued in 1972 and 1993 respectively. ",
            "keyString": "793366s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "New freight corridors announced at ________",
            "optionA": "  Delhi - Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Kharagpur - Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Kharagpur - Vijayawada ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat - Agra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew freight corridors announced at Gujarat - Agra. ",
            "keyString": "793393s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In context with the Indian railways what is TPWS?",
            "optionA": "  Train Passenger Warning System ",
            "optionB": "  Train Protection Warning System ",
            "optionC": "  Train Protection Warning Stopper ",
            "optionD": "  Transmission Protection warning Stopper ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrain Protection Warning System ",
            "keyString": "793407s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where was the B.B.C.I locomotive started?",
            "optionA": "  Jamalpur ",
            "optionB": "  Parel ",
            "optionC": "  Boriville ",
            "optionD": "  Hyderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "793419s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Food Safety and Standards Authority of India (FSSAI) certified ________ as India's first Eat Right Station.",
            "optionA": "  Chennai Central railway station ",
            "optionB": "  Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj railway station ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai Central railway station ",
            "optionD": "  Bengaluru Central railway station ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMumbai Central gets India's first 'Eat Right Station', 4-star rating by FSSAI. MUMBAI : The Mumbai Central Terminus of the Western Railway has been certified as India's first \"Eat Right Station\" with a 4-Star rating awarded by the FSSAI. ",
            "keyString": "793430s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which train in India has the longest route length?",
            "optionA": "  Howrah - Jammu Tawi Himgiri Express ",
            "optionB": "  Kanyakumari - Jammu Tawi Himsagar Express ",
            "optionC": "  Kanyakumari - Dibrugarh Vivek Express ",
            "optionD": "  Guwahati - Tiruvananthapuram Express ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVivek Express \u2013 Dibrugarh to Kanyakumari. With a running time of 82 hours 45 minutes (3.5 days) and about 56 scheduled stops, the Vivek Express covers the longest train route in India. It originates in northern Assam and goes all the way to the southern tip of India to Kanyakumari. ",
            "keyString": "825353s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following two countries have largest electrified railway network in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Russia & US ",
            "optionB": "  US & China ",
            "optionC": "  Russia & China ",
            "optionD": "  India & US ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRussia & China are two countries that have largest electrified railway network in the world. ",
            "keyString": "825381s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Launched three Trains to improve Quality of Travel (for reserved passengers), these are:",
            "optionA": "  Humsafar, Tejas and Uday ",
            "optionB": "  Tejas, Antyodaya and Gatiman ",
            "optionC": "  Dirubhargh, Sahayak and Humsafar ",
            "optionD": "  Sahayak,Antyodaya and Gatiman ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHumsafar, Tejas and Uday. ",
            "keyString": "825394s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following sectors:1)Plantation Sector2)Mining and Exploration of Metal 3)Railway InfrastructureIn which of the above, government has permitted 100% FDI through automatic route?",
            "optionA": "  1 & 2 Only ",
            "optionB": "  3 Only ",
            "optionC": "  2 & 3 Only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll three. ",
            "keyString": "825405s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Elphinstone Road suburban railway station which was recently renamed as Prabhadevi is situated in?",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Bengaluru ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrabhadevi railway station. Prabhadevi railway station (formerly Elphinstone Road, station code: EPR), is a railway station on the Western line of the Mumbai Suburban Railway in Mumbai, India. It has two platforms, on which only slow trains halt. A footbridge links Prabhadevi to Parel station on the Central Line. ",
            "keyString": "825418s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In diesel engine, ignition is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Spark ",
            "optionB": "  Automatic starter ",
            "optionC": "  Compression ",
            "optionD": "  Friction ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe diesel engine (also known as a compression-ignition or CI engine), named after Rudolf Diesel, is an internal combustion engine in which ignition of the fuel is caused by the elevated temperature of the air in the cylinder due to the mechanical compression (adiabatic compression). ",
            "keyString": "858090s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is India\u2019s first green railway corridor?",
            "optionA": "  Barmer to Munawab ",
            "optionB": "  Manamadurai to Rameswaram ",
            "optionC": "  Chennai to Manamadurai ",
            "optionD": "  Puri to Visakhapatnam ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nation's first Green Rail Corridor, a 114-km long Rameswaram-Manamadurai stretch in Tamil Nadu which ensures zero toilet discharge on rail tracks, was inaugurated by Railways Minister Suresh Prabhu. ",
            "keyString": "858119s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest marshalling yard in India (also the longest in Asia)?",
            "optionA": "  Mughalsarai ",
            "optionB": "  Mathura ",
            "optionC": "  Itarsi ",
            "optionD": "  Guntakal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMughalsarai marshalling yard is the largest in Asia. It is 12.5 km long and handles around 1,500 wagons daily. ",
            "keyString": "858133s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest railway junction in India?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Bhatinda ",
            "optionC": "  Mathura ",
            "optionD": "  Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\u200b\u200b\u200b\u200b\u200b\u200b\u200bMathura junction is the largest railway junction in India, with as many as 7 routes emerging from this station. Mathura junction also has 10 platforms, with connectivity to all major cities of India.",
            "keyString": "858145s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many training institutions of Railways are in India?",
            "optionA": "  Three ",
            "optionB": "  Four ",
            "optionC": "  Five ",
            "optionD": "  Six ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFive training institutions of Railways are in India. ",
            "keyString": "858156s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which of the following places steam engines were originally manufactured by Indian Railway ?",
            "optionA": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionB": "  Perambur ",
            "optionC": "  Chittranjan ",
            "optionD": "  Patiala ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSteam engines were originally manufactured by Indian Railway at Chittranjan. ",
            "keyString": "891330s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which year is declared as \"Year of Rail Users\" by the Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  2000 ",
            "optionB": "  1995 ",
            "optionC": "  1996 ",
            "optionD": "  1997 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t1995 is declared as \"Year of Rail Users\" by the Indian Railways. ",
            "keyString": "891363s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who has been appointed the new Financial Commissioner (FC) of Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  A K Prasad ",
            "optionB": "  S K Bhagat ",
            "optionC": "  Anand Mathur ",
            "optionD": "  Akhil Agrawal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShri A.K. Prasad has been appointed as new Financial Commissioner (Railways), Railway Board and ex-officio Secretary to Government of India vice Shri B.N. Mohapatra, who superannuated on 31st January, 2018. ",
            "keyString": "891378s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has been adjudged as the cleanest railway station in category A1, as per recently released report by the Ministry of Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Vishakhapatnam ",
            "optionB": "  Jammu Tawi ",
            "optionC": "  Secunderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Anand ViharTerminal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "891390s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the longest station name in Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Kanyakumari ",
            "optionB": "  Venkatanarasimharajuvaripeta ",
            "optionC": "  Kharagpur ",
            "optionD": "  Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVenkatanarasimharajuvaripeta is the Railway Station with the longest name in India. ",
            "keyString": "891401s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "First Train started in India?",
            "optionA": "  1851 ",
            "optionB": "  1852 ",
            "optionC": "  1853 ",
            "optionD": "  1854 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first passenger train in India ran between Bombay (Bori Bunder) and Thane on 16 April 1853. The 14-carriage train was hauled by three steam locomotives: Sahib, Sindh and Sultan. ",
            "keyString": "924208s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year the practice of presenting the railway budget separate from the general budget (or vice versa in true sense) started in India?",
            "optionA": "  1920 ",
            "optionB": "  1924 ",
            "optionC": "  1925 ",
            "optionD": "  1930 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSeparate Railway budget was introduced in 1924 on the recommendations of the Acworth committee. After 92 years in 2018 Railway Budget merged with General Budget was based on the recommendations of the Committee headed by Bibek Debroy, then a member of the NITI Aayog.",
            "keyString": "924237s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How much distance was travelled by first train of India?",
            "optionA": "  33 km ",
            "optionB": "  36 km ",
            "optionC": "  34 km ",
            "optionD": "  46 km ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's first train ran from Mumbai to Thane in 1853. The first train on the Indian sub-continent ran from Bori Bunder in Mumbai to Thane at 3.30 pm on April 16, 1853. The 14-carriage train carried 400 guests and covered a distance of 34 km. ",
            "keyString": "924252s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which Governor - General's reign railway lines in India were established?",
            "optionA": "  Lord William Bentick ",
            "optionB": "  Lord Cornwallis ",
            "optionC": "  Lord Kenning ",
            "optionD": "  Lord Dalhousie ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe country's first passenger train, which ran between Bombay's Bori Bunder station and Thane on 16 April 1853, was dedicated by Lord Dalhousie. Therefore, railway lines in India were established during Lord Dalhousie's reign. ",
            "keyString": "924264s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the width of broad gauge railway line in India?",
            "optionA": "  5 feet 3 inches ",
            "optionB": "  5 feet 6 inches ",
            "optionC": "  4 feet 11 inches ",
            "optionD": "  5 feet 4 inches ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Railways has currently 4 different gauges. The Broad Gauge which is 1676 mm or 5 feet 6 inches ",
            "keyString": "924279s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which of the following is the longest railway bridge in India located?",
            "optionA": "  River Ganges ",
            "optionB": "  Vembanad Lake ",
            "optionC": "  River Brahmaputra ",
            "optionD": "  Chilka Lake ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Vembanad Rail Bridge is located in the state of Kerala and connects Edappally and Vallarpadam in Kochi. Vembanad rail bridge is the longest rail bridge in India with the total length of 4.62 km. ",
            "keyString": "956262s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At what time the first train in Indian (and in Asia) flagged off?",
            "optionA": "  Saturday, 8:50 AM ",
            "optionB": "  Sunday, 10:00 AM ",
            "optionC": "  Saturday, 03:35 PM ",
            "optionD": "  Sunday, 02:30 PM ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first train in India (and Asia) ran over a short distance of 34 kilometres (21 miles) on 16 April 1853 between Bombay and Thane. Hauled by three engines \u2014 Sindh, Sahib and Sultan \u2014 the original train had fourteen coaches and 400 guests as passengers. It left Bombay at 3:35 pm and reached Thane in 57 minutes. ",
            "keyString": "956290s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the position of the Indian Railway in the world according to the length of rail lines?",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Fourth ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railways is the 4th largest railway network in the world preceded by US (250, 000Km), China (100000Km), and Russia (85000Km). ",
            "keyString": "956303s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was Petrol Rail car started on Kalka - Shimla Rail route?",
            "optionA": "  1911 ",
            "optionB": "  1913 ",
            "optionC": "  1918 ",
            "optionD": "  1917 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPetrol Rail car started on Kalka - Shimla Rail route in 1911. ",
            "keyString": "956315s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the position of the Indian Railway under the zonal system?",
            "optionA": "  First ",
            "optionB": "  Second ",
            "optionC": "  Third ",
            "optionD": "  Forth ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe position of the Indian Railway under the zonal system is second. ",
            "keyString": "956325s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following zones administers the Matheran Hill Railway?",
            "optionA": "  Konkan Railways ",
            "optionB": "  Western Railways ",
            "optionC": "  Central Railways ",
            "optionD": "  Southern Railways ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMatheran Hill Railway. The Matheran Hill Railway (MHR) is a 2 ft (610 mm) narrow-gauge heritage railway in Maharashtra, India, which is administered by the Central Railway. ",
            "keyString": "989232s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Railway will be provided a device to their Gang Men which would be wireless enabled and will intimate them about approaching trains. The Device will be called:",
            "optionA": "  Surakhsha ",
            "optionB": "  Rail Rakshak ",
            "optionC": "  Shaktimaan ",
            "optionD": "  Rakshak ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailway Minister announced that all our gang men will be provided with devices called 'Rakshak' which would be wireless enabled and will intimate them about approaching trains. Indian Railways will also reduce the weight of the tools carried by them while patrolling on foot through value engineering. ",
            "keyString": "989260s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the gauges is used in the hilly areas?",
            "optionA": "  Broad gauge ",
            "optionB": "  Meter gauge ",
            "optionC": "  Narrow gauge ",
            "optionD": "  Special gauge ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNarrow gauge is used in the hilly areas. ",
            "keyString": "989273s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first Shatabdi express was introduced between which of the following locations?",
            "optionA": "  Bombay and Thane ",
            "optionB": "  Bombay and Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  New Delhi and Jhansi ",
            "optionD": "  New Delhi and Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Shatabdi Express train was introduced in 1988, by then Railways Minister Madhavrao Scindia to commemorate the birth centenary of Jawaharlal Nehru the first Prime Minister of India, between New Delhi and Jhansi Junction. ",
            "keyString": "989284s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through which of the following group of states does the Konkan Railways run?",
            "optionA": "  Maharashtra - Karnataka - Andhra Pradesh - Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Maharashtra - Karnataka - Goa  ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra - Karnataka - Kerala - Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Karnataka - Goa - Kerala - Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 741-km (461-mi) line connects the states of Maharashtra, Goa and Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "989295s6m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following is known for having designed the first railway timetables?",
            "optionA": "  George Bradman ",
            "optionB": "  George Bernard Shaw ",
            "optionC": "  George Bradshaw ",
            "optionD": "  George Brummel ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGeorge Bradshaw is known for having designed the first railway timetables. ",
            "keyString": "21140s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which institution the training of electric work is being given?",
            "optionA": "  Indian Railways Institute of Mechanical and Electrical Engineering ",
            "optionB": "  Indian Railways Institute of Electrical Engineering ",
            "optionC": "  Railway Staff College ",
            "optionD": "  Indian Railways Institute of Civil Engineering ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railways Institute of Electrical Engineering (IRIEEN), Nashik was set up by the Indian Railways at Nashik in Maharashtra for imparting training to newly appointed officers of Indian Railway Service of Electrical Engineers (IRSEE), recruited through Engineering Services Examination conducted by UPSC, New Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "21168s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year Indian Railway was nationalized?",
            "optionA": "  1947 ",
            "optionB": "  1951 ",
            "optionC": "  1952 ",
            "optionD": "  1955 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailways were first introduced to India in 1853. By 1947, the year of India's independence, there were forty-two rail systems. In 1951 the systems were nationalised as one unit, becoming one of the largest networks in the world. ",
            "keyString": "21180s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Railway Staff College is situated at",
            "optionA": "  Bangalore ",
            "optionB": "  Secunderabad ",
            "optionC": "  Chennai ",
            "optionD": "  Vadodara ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailway Staff College (now called as National Academy of Indian Railways) is a centralised training institute for Group A and Group B officers of Indian Railways located in Lalbaug-Manjalpur area of Vadodara (Gujarat). ",
            "keyString": "21192s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements with respect to Railway Freight corridor projects in India:1)The Eastern freight corridor extends from Dankuni in Bengal to Ludhiana in Punjab and it is funded by World Bank2)The Western freight corridor extends from Jawaharlal Nehru port in Mumbai to Dadri near Delhi and it is funded by Japan International Cooperation AgencyWhich of the above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Eastern freight corridor extends from Dankuni in Bengal to Ludhiana in Punjab and it is funded by World Bank and the Western freight corridor extends from Jawaharlal Nehru port in Mumbai to Dadri near Delhi and it is funded by Japan International Cooperation Agency. ",
            "keyString": "21202s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following committee gave recommendations on separation of Policy - making, Regulation & Operations in Indian Railways and setting up of a Railway Regulatory Authority of India (RRAI)?",
            "optionA": "  Bibek Deberoy committee ",
            "optionB": "  Rangarajan committee ",
            "optionC": "  Rajinder Sachar Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Mihir Shah Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe committee chaired by Bibek Debroy had inter-alia recommended concessioning of commercial operation of train service like Rajdhani/Shatabdi to private parties. ",
            "keyString": "53912s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Presentation of the first ever railway budget in India held in",
            "optionA": "  1853 ",
            "optionB": "  1888 ",
            "optionC": "  1925 ",
            "optionD": "  1905 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "53939s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about the Railway Convention Committee:1)It consists of members from Lok Sabha only2)Chairman of Railway Convention Committee is appointed by Lok Sabha speakerWhich among the above statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChairman of Railway Convention Committee is appointed by Lok Sabha speaker. ",
            "keyString": "53952s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about the Railwire Saathi project:1)It is an initiative by the Indian Railway Stations Development Corporation Limited (IRSDC)2)It aims to provide railway stations in India with high - speed public Wi - Fi serviceWhich of the above statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt aims to provide railway stations in India with high - speed public Wi - Fi service. ",
            "keyString": "53966s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The world\u2019s highest railway bridge will come up over which Indian River?",
            "optionA": "  Narmada ",
            "optionB": "  Godavari ",
            "optionC": "  Ganga ",
            "optionD": "  Chenab ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chenab Bridge is an Indian railway steel and concrete arch bridge under construction between Bakkal and Kauri in the Reasi district of Jammu and Kashmir in India. When completed, the bridge will span the Chenab River at a height of 359 m (1,178 ft) above the river, making it the world's highest rail bridge. ",
            "keyString": "53979s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which railway zone has become the first Rail Zone in India with 100% LED Lighting at railway stations?",
            "optionA": "  North Eastern Railway ",
            "optionB": "  South Central Railway ",
            "optionC": "  South Western Railway ",
            "optionD": "  North Central Railway ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe South Central Railway (SCR) has become the first railway zone in India to complete 100% LED lighting at all the 733 stations under its jurisdiction. ",
            "keyString": "86256s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following stations was formerly known as Victoria Terminus?",
            "optionA": "  Churchgate Railway Station ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai Central ",
            "optionC": "  Lokmanya Tilak Terminus ",
            "optionD": "  Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChhatrapati Shivaji Terminus (officially Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj Terminus) (station code: CSTM (mainline)/ST (suburban)), also known by its former name Victoria Terminus (station code: BBVT/VT), is a historic terminal train station and UNESCO World Heritage Site in Mumbai, Maharashtra, India. ",
            "keyString": "86284s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "2 states of North East India will be connected through Broad Gauge. They are:",
            "optionA": "  Manipur and Meghalaya ",
            "optionB": "  Mizoram and Manipur ",
            "optionC": "  Meghalaya and Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMizoram and Manipur will be connected through Broad Gauge. ",
            "keyString": "86297s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the first underground railway (Metro Railway) started?",
            "optionA": "  1982 ",
            "optionB": "  1989 ",
            "optionC": "  1984 ",
            "optionD": "  1992 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kolkata Metro was the first metro railway in India, opening for commercial services from 1984. ",
            "keyString": "86309s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On November 14, 2019, With which locomotive factory, Indian Railways & French multinational company Alstom have entered into procurement cum maintenance agreement to deliver the 10 locomotives in FY (fiscal year) 2019 - 20?",
            "optionA": "  Modern Coach Factory ",
            "optionB": "  Integral Coach Factory ",
            "optionC": "  Rail Wheel Factory ",
            "optionD": "  Madhepura Electric Locomotive Pvt. Ltd. (MELPL) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn November 14, 2019, to deliver the 10 locomotives in FY (fiscal year) 2019-20, Indian Railways & French multinational company Alstom have entered into procurement cum maintenance agreement with Bihar based Madhepura Electric Locomotive Pvt. Ltd. ",
            "keyString": "86319s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Research, Design and Standard Organisation situated?",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Bangalore ",
            "optionC": "  Pune ",
            "optionD": "  New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1957, the Central Standards Office (CSO) and the Railway Testing and Research Centre (RTRC) were integrated into a single unit named Research Designs and Standards Organisation (RDSO) under the Ministry of Railways with its headquarters at Manak Nagar, Lucknow. ",
            "keyString": "118555s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the wheel and axle plant of Indian Railways situated?",
            "optionA": "  Chittranjan ",
            "optionB": "  Kapurthala ",
            "optionC": "  Bangalore ",
            "optionD": "  Perambur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRail Wheel Factory, Yelehanka (RWF) (also known as Wheel and Axle Plant) is a manufacturing unit of Indian Railways, producing wheels, axles and wheel sets of railroad wagons, coaches and locomotives for the use of Indian Railways and overseas customers is situated at Yelahanka, Bangalore in the Indian state of Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "118583s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Indian Railways Institute of Mechanical and Electrical Engineering institute situated?",
            "optionA": "  Nasik ",
            "optionB": "  Baroda ",
            "optionC": "  Jamalpur ",
            "optionD": "  Pune ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indian Railways Institute of Mechanical and Electrical Engineering (IRIMEE), was founded in 1888 as a technical school and commenced training Mechanical Officers for Indian Railways in 1927. It is the oldest of the five Centralised Training Institutes (CTIs) for training officers for Indian Railways. IRIMEE is located at Jamalpur in the Munger district of Bihar, on the Patna-Bhagalpur rail route. ",
            "keyString": "118597s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the Indian Railways Institute of Civil Engineering Institute situated?",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Nasik ",
            "optionD": "  Secunderabad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railways Institute of Civil Engineering (IRICEN), Pune is the training institute for the Civil engineers of the Indian Railways.",
            "keyString": "118608s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India\u2019s first Antyodaya Express has been launched by the Minister of Railways. The express will run between which stations?",
            "optionA": "  Ernakulam and Howrah ",
            "optionB": "  Sriganganagar and Tiruchirapalli ",
            "optionC": "  New Delhi and Kanyakumari ",
            "optionD": "  Nizamuddin and Palakkad ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Union Minister of Railways Suresh Prabhu has flagged off India\u2019s first Antyodaya Express between Ernakulam and Howrah. The train service was inaugurated by the Railways Minister via video conferencing in New Delhi on February 27, 2017. The Antyodaya Express is a long-distance, fully unreserved, superfast train service, for the common man to be operated on dense routes. The new express train will have facilities like cushioned luggage racks which can serve as seats, LED lights, modular toilets, pleasing interior colour scheme and others. Beside this, the Railway Minister has also flagged off the 4th Humsafar Express between Sriganganagar and Tiruchirapalli. The new train is fully air-conditioned third AC service with an optional service for meals. ",
            "keyString": "118619s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements about Railway Convention Committee:1)The Chairman of the Committee is appointed by the Speaker from amongst the members of the Committee2) The Committee reviews the rate of dividend which is payable by the Railway Undertaking to the General RevenuesWhich of the above statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 Only ",
            "optionB": "  2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 & 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chairman of the Committee is appointed by the Speaker from amongst the members of the Committee and The Committee reviews the rate of dividend which is payable by the Railway Undertaking to the General Revenues. ",
            "keyString": "184581s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the main source of earning of Railway?",
            "optionA": "  Goods fair ",
            "optionB": "  Passenger fair ",
            "optionC": "  Catering ",
            "optionD": "  None of thses ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFreight is one of the major sources of income for Indian Railways. ",
            "keyString": "184612s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has become the India\u2019s first railway station to have sanitary napkin vending machine?",
            "optionA": "  Thane railway station ",
            "optionB": "  Hazrat Nizamuddin railway station ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata railway station ",
            "optionD": "  Bhopal railway station ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Bhopal railway station has become the India's first railway station to have a sanitary napkin vending machine named as 'Happy Nari'. The machine dispenses two sanitary napkins at the cost of Rs 5 only and accepts Rs 5 coins. ",
            "keyString": "184625s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Railway will publish new Magazine in all regional language. The name of that Magazine is:",
            "optionA": "  Rail Line ",
            "optionB": "  Big Thing, Big Way ",
            "optionC": "  Rail Prakashan ",
            "optionD": "  Rail Bandhu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe railway magazine, Rail Bandhu, will be now published in all regional languages and would be available for purchase to reserved passengers. ",
            "keyString": "184637s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Seikan Tunnel which is a Railway tunnel with less than half length under seabed is located in which country?",
            "optionA": "  Japan ",
            "optionB": "  South Korea ",
            "optionC": "  North Korea ",
            "optionD": "  China ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 53.85km Seikan tunnel in Japan is the longest and deepest rail tunnel in the world. It passes through Tsugaru Strait connecting the Hokkaido and Honshu islands. It was built 100m below the seabed and includes a 23.3km submarine portion. ",
            "keyString": "184648s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which railway station entered Limca Book of Records 2018 for having all - women staff?",
            "optionA": "  Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus railway station ",
            "optionB": "  Matunga railway station ",
            "optionC": "  Hazrat Nizamuddin railway station ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata railway station ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Matunga suburban station on the Central Railway (CR) of Mumbai division has figured in the Limca Book of Records 2018 for having an all-woman staff. The achievement comes six months after Matunga became the first railway station in the country to be run by an all-woman staff. ",
            "keyString": "216353s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which railway station has become the India\u2019s first station to run by all women staff?",
            "optionA": "  Matunga railway station ",
            "optionB": "  Hazrat Nizamuddin railway station ",
            "optionC": "  Chhatrapati Shivaji Terminus railway station ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata railway station ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Matunga suburban station on the Central Railway (CR) of Mumbai division has figured in the Limca Book of Records 2018 for having an all-woman staff. The achievement comes six months after Matunga became the first railway station in the country to be run by an all-woman staff. ",
            "keyString": "216381s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In how many zones Indian Railway has been divided?",
            "optionA": "  14 ",
            "optionB": "  16 ",
            "optionC": "  17 ",
            "optionD": "  20 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railways is divided into 17 zones, which are further sub-divided into divisions. The number of zones in Indian Railways increased from six to eight in 1951, nine in 1966 and sixteen in 2003. Each zonal railway is made up of a certain number of divisions, each having a divisional headquarters. ",
            "keyString": "216395s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When was the Jammu City appeared on the map of Indian Railway?",
            "optionA": "  1956 ",
            "optionB": "  1963 ",
            "optionC": "  1967 ",
            "optionD": "  1965 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJammu City appeared on the map of Indian Railway in 1965. ",
            "keyString": "216406s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following stations has all the three gauges viz. broad, metre and narrow?",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Chandigarh ",
            "optionC": "  Shimla ",
            "optionD": "  Siliguri ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSiliguri Junction is one of the three railway stations that serves the city of Siliguri located in Darjeeling district in the Indian state of West Bengal. The other two stations are: Siliguri Town and New Jalpaiguri. It has 1,676 mm (5 ft 6 in) broad gauge and Narrow Gauge tracks. It formerly had the distinction of having three gauges but the metre-gauge line from Aluabari Road to Siliguri Junction was converted later into broad gauge. Few years ago train bus used to run between Siliguri Junction to naksalbari by the metre gauge line. ",
            "keyString": "216417s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the headquarters of the newly established railway zone 'East Coast Railways'?",
            "optionA": "  Visakhapatnam ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Hyderabad ",
            "optionD": "  Bhubaneswar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe East Coast Railway (abbreviated ECoR) is one of the 18 railway zones of Indian Railways. It came into existence on 1 April 2003. The headquarters of the zone are at Bhubaneswar. ",
            "keyString": "249376s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Headquarters of which one among the following Railway Zones in India is situated at the highest elevation from the mean sea level?",
            "optionA": "  East Central Railway ",
            "optionB": "  South Eastern Railway ",
            "optionC": "  South Western Railway ",
            "optionD": "  West Central Railway ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHeadquarters of South Western Railway is situated at the highest elevation from the mean sea level. ",
            "keyString": "249403s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to headquarters of the various Railway zones, consider the following matches:North Eastern \u2192 Guwahati Central \u2192 Bhopal Western \u2192 MumbaiWhich of the above is / are correct matches:",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 1 & 2 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 2 & 3 ",
            "optionD": "  Only 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWestern \u2192 Mumbai is correct. ",
            "keyString": "249416s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The headquarter of Central Railway situated at?",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai (CST) ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai (Church Gate) ",
            "optionC": "  Gwalior ",
            "optionD": "  Gorakhpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMumbai (CST) is the headquarter of Central Railway. ",
            "keyString": "249430s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The monies in the National Investment Fund can be used for ________:1. Recapitalization of public sector banks2. Purchasing the shares of CPSEs3. Towards operating expenses of Indian Railways4. Social Overheads such as building schools, toilets etc.Select the correct option from the codes given below:",
            "optionA": "  Only 1, 2 & 3 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2, 3 & 4 ",
            "optionC": "  Only 1, 2 & 4 ",
            "optionD": "  Only 1 & 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe monies in the National Investment Fund can be used for recapitalization of public sector banks and purchasing the shares of CPSEs. ",
            "keyString": "249441s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mughalsarai junction has recently renamed as Deen Dayal Upadhyaya railway station. It is located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Bihar ",
            "optionB": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "optionD": "  Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeen Dayal Upadhyaya Junction, station code: DDU, formerly MGS), is a railway station in the Indian state of Uttar Pradesh. The station contains the largest railway marshaling yard in Asia. Mughalsarai yard cater to around 450-500 trains in a month. ",
            "keyString": "282576s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Matheran Hill Railway is a narrow gauge heritage railway located in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Matheran Hill Railway (MHR) is a 2 ft (610 mm) narrow-gauge heritage railway in Maharashtra, India, which is administered by the Central Railway. It covers a distance of 21 km (13 mi), cutting a swathe through forest and connecting Neral to Matheran in the Western Ghats. ",
            "keyString": "282604s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian railways has installed Asia\u2019s largest Solid State Interlocking (SSI) system in which state?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Punjab ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railways has installed Asia's largest Solid State Interlocking (SSI) system at Kharagpur in West Bengal. The system will enable station masters to set 800 different routes for trains in a matter of minutes. ",
            "keyString": "282617s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which city is hosting the International Conference on Green Initiatives & Railway Electrification?",
            "optionA": "  Kochi ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Guwahati ",
            "optionD": "  New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe International Conference on Green Initiatives & Railway Electrification was hosted in New Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "282628s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest zone in terms of route kilometers?",
            "optionA": "  Western Railways ",
            "optionB": "  Eastern Railways ",
            "optionC": "  Northern Railways ",
            "optionD": "  Southern Railways ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorthern Railway zone is the Answer. Its headquarter is New Delhi Railway Station. Northern Railways is one of nine old zones of Indian Railways and also the biggest in terms of network having 6807 kilometre route. ",
            "keyString": "282639s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Shatabdi Express train was started in ________.",
            "optionA": "  1984 ",
            "optionB": "  1988 ",
            "optionC": "  1990 ",
            "optionD": "  1985 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first Shatabdi Express train was introduced in 1988, by then Railways Minister Madhavrao Scindia to commemorate the birth centenary of Jawaharlal Nehru the first Prime Minister of India, between New Delhi and Jhansi Junction. ",
            "keyString": "315881s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the shortest station name in Indian Railways?",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Bc ",
            "optionC": "  Goa ",
            "optionD": "  Ib ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIb is a railway station in the Indian state of Odisha. It has the distinction of having the shortest name of all stations on the Indian Railways system. ",
            "keyString": "315909s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A separate Railway Budget, which is different from the General Budget, was first introduced in 1924 on the basis of recommendations of the 10 - member:",
            "optionA": "  Acworth Committee ",
            "optionB": "  Srinivas Shastri Committee ",
            "optionC": "  Rail Budget Committee ",
            "optionD": "  Sultan Committee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA separate Railway Budget, which is different from the General Budget, was first introduced in 1924 on the basis of recommendations of the 10-member Acworth Committee. ",
            "keyString": "315922s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The shuttle train service between Lahore and ________ railway station resumed its operation on 15 December after a gap of 22 years.",
            "optionA": "  Wagah ",
            "optionB": "  Islamabad ",
            "optionC": "  Amritsar ",
            "optionD": "  Faridkot ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe shuttle train service between Lahore and Wagah railway station resumed operation on Sunday after a gap of 22 years.",
            "keyString": "315933s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Diesel locomotives are built in?",
            "optionA": "  Banglore ",
            "optionB": "  Varanasi ",
            "optionC": "  Perambur ",
            "optionD": "  Hubli ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Diesel Locomotive Works (DLW) in Varanasi, India, is a production unit of Indian Railways, that manufactures diesel-electric locomotives and its spare parts. ",
            "keyString": "315943s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following cities, the first subway train was started?",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Delhi ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Chennai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kolkata Metro was the first metro railway in India, opening for commercial services from 1984. ",
            "keyString": "347910s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Between which of the destinations the first Indian train was started?",
            "optionA": "  From Kolkata to Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  From Mumbai to Thane ",
            "optionC": "  From Mumbai to Surat ",
            "optionD": "  From Mumbai to Madras ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first passenger train in India ran between Bombay (Bori Bunder) and Thane on 16 April 1853. ",
            "keyString": "347938s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following:1)Real Estate Investment Trust2)Railway operation3)Atomic EnergyAs of now, there is no FDI in India, in which of above sector(s)?",
            "optionA": "  1 Only ",
            "optionB": "  1 & 2 Only ",
            "optionC": "  1, 2 & 3 ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll three ",
            "keyString": "347950s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Is general manager responsible for?",
            "optionA": "  Railway Board ",
            "optionB": "  Railway Ministry ",
            "optionC": "  Both railway Board and Railway Ministry ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRailway Board. ",
            "keyString": "347965s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the wheel and axle plant of Indian Railways situated ?",
            "optionA": "  Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Bangalore ",
            "optionC": "  Mysore ",
            "optionD": "  Chitradurga ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRail Wheel Factory, Yelehanka (RWF) (also known as Wheel and Axle Plant) is a manufacturing unit of Indian Railways, producing wheels, axles and wheel sets of railroad wagons, coaches and locomotives for the use of Indian Railways and overseas customers is situated at Yelahanka, Bangalore in the Indian state of Karnataka. ",
            "keyString": "347975s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian Railways which is the largest of the Public Sector Enterprises, is divided in how many regions?",
            "optionA": "  7 ",
            "optionB": "  9 ",
            "optionC": "  8 ",
            "optionD": "  10 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian Railways which is the largest of the Public Sector Enterprises, is divided in 9 regions. ",
            "keyString": "379957s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the extreme north of India a railway station?",
            "optionA": "  Jammu Tawi ",
            "optionB": "  Baramulla ",
            "optionC": "  Pathankot ",
            "optionD": "  Guwahati ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's northernmost railway station is Baramulla in Jammu and Kashmir, and the westernmost is Naliya near Gujarat's Bhuj. Kanyakumari is the last railway station in the south, while on the east, it is Ledo on branch line from Tinsukia. ",
            "keyString": "379985s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which state to have India\u2019s first privately - run railway station?",
            "optionA": "  Tripura ",
            "optionB": "  Odisha ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt's in Bhopal. This is the rendered site-image of Habibganj railway station in Bhopal. This will be the first station in the country to be developed under private partnership. Indian Railway Stations Development Corporation has announced that Habibganj station will be developed according to international standards. ",
            "keyString": "379997s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India\u2019s first solar - powered 1600 HP DEMU train has launched from which railway station?",
            "optionA": "  Farukhnagar railway station ",
            "optionB": "  Safdarjung railway station ",
            "optionC": "  Habibganj railway station ",
            "optionD": "  Mumbai Central railway station ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's first 1600 HP solar-powered DEMU train was launched from Safdarjung railway station. It will run from Sarai Rohilla in Delhi to Farukh Nagar in Haryana. ",
            "keyString": "380009s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following will become the first central paramilitary force to opt for e - ticketing instead of Railway warrant?",
            "optionA": "  Assam Rifles ",
            "optionB": "  National Security Guard ",
            "optionC": "  Central Reserve Police Force ",
            "optionD": "  Sashastra Seema Bal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe National Security Guard will be the first central paramilitary force to opt for e-ticketing instead of the railway warrant under an agreement signed with the IRCTC, a statement from the catering and tourism arm of the railways said today. ",
            "keyString": "380019s7m58h12d14m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}